Hello English learners. Welcome
back to English Pod. My name is Marco.
And my name is Catherine.
Today we've got a very,
very useful lesson
for all of you out there.
That's right. We're
bringing you part two of
the What If series,
which is a small series.
Small. And it is kind of grammar focused,
but it's very, very important because
you often want to talk about
things that don't happen.
We're calling these hypotheticals
or a conditional statement.
Right. So there are many different types
of hypotheticals or conditional statements.
So today we're going
to be looking at the third
conditional, which is
probably the hardest one
because it uses a little bit of
a complex grammar structure.
It's complex and we're
actually talking about things
that did not happen and
that will not happen, right?
It's impossible to change. It's
impossible to change these because
there are things that would have
happened in the past, but didn't.
Wow, that sounds confusing. Why
don't we listen to the dialogue for
the first time and then we'll be
back to look at some phrases first.
This is the good life.
We have a good, don't you think?
Yeah, of course. Although don't you
ever wonder what could have been?
What do you mean?
Well, sometimes I think
of how things could have
turned out if I had done
things a little differently.
For example, like for
example, if I hadn't studied
architecture, I would have
become an artist like I wanted to.
I see. Yeah, now that I
think of it, I wouldn't have
gotten married if I hadn't
moved to this town in Met Sally.
You see, everything happens
for a reason. We wouldn't even
have met if I hadn't been in
that car accident ten years ago.
Well, I have no regrets.
I'll drink to that.
All right, so two guys,
you know, talking about life.
I imagine these guys as being, you
know, middle-to-middle age or a little bit
older, sitting on a porch, drinking and
beer, talking about what could have been.
Yeah, exactly. They're
kind of thinking about
the past and the
decisions they have made.
Yeah, exactly. All right, so before
we start in the grammar, why don't
we take a look at a couple of
different phrases on Fluency Builder?
Fluency Builder.
Well, Marco, this first phrase is a
phrase you'll hear very often in English.
It's a phrase that even has philosophical
roots, something we talked a lot about
when we're studying Socrates back in the
end of school, but this is the good life.
The good life. We have the
good life or I have a good life.
I have a good life is a very common phrase,
but here, the good life is an idiom.
So I'm living the good life. It means, you
know, I have no complaints about my life.
Right, so pretty much you
have all your necessities covered.
And maybe you have a good,
a nice family and you have a
good job and you're just
happy, so this is the good life.
Very good, so you have the good life.
Now, moving on to another
phrase, it's kind of also a
philosophical, you know, it says
everything happens for a reason.
All right, so this phrase is,
well, it's also pretty common.
People say this when bad things happen, but
they also say this when good things happen.
So basically, you're just
saying that it's destiny.
If this bad thing happened
to you, there is a reason for it.
Maybe you don't see it now, maybe not
tomorrow, but maybe later you'll see why.
This often happens when
people lose their jobs.
You say, well, you know,
everything happens for a reason.
Maybe losing this job will
allow you to find a better job.
Or maybe go back to school and study.
Or maybe meet the man
or woman of your dreams.
Right, so everything happens
for a reason, very good.
And then the guy agrees
and says, well, I'll drink to that.
Okay, so this is a way for people speaking
English to say, listen, I agree with you.
I like that idea and I will cheers.
Cheers, right.
Right, so this means we're going to
touch our glasses or touch our beer bottles
and we're going to, you know, think
about how this is a nice thought, you know.
Everything happens
for a reason is positive.
It's a way to say, listen, good
things can happen from us.
Right, so he's saying, yes, I agree.
Cheers.
I'll drink to that.
All right, well, pretty
interesting phrases.
You know, they're very common,
I guess, like, colloquial, right?
So you can use them in everyday
conversation with a friend.
You can.
And, you know, oftentimes we say,
for example, something really positive.
Like, I'm really glad I
have such great friends.
And then everyone
says, oh, I'll drink to that.
Right, and so this is
something you'll hear
when you're out with
friends or with family.
And they may sound funny at
first, but you will recognize them
when you're speaking to
people who speak English.
All right, so right, so let's
listen to our dialogue again
and then we'll come back
and explain the grammar.
[MUSIC]
This is the good life.
We have it good, don't you think?
Yeah, of course.
Although, don't you ever
wonder what could have been?
What do you mean?
Well, sometimes I think of how
things could have turned out
if I had done things a little differently.
For example, like, for example,
if I hadn't studied architecture,
I would have become
an artist like I wanted to.
I see.
Yeah, now that I think of it, I
wouldn't have gotten married
if I hadn't moved to
this town in Met Sally.
You see, everything happens for a reason.
We wouldn't even have met if I hadn't
been in that car accident ten years ago.
Well, I have no regrets.
I'll drink to that.
[MUSIC]
All right, so now it's time
for grammar breakdown.
Rama Breakdown.
So in grammar breakdown, we're going to
look at the two main parts of these phrases
that allow us to talk about
things that didn't happen.
So we're talking about
looking back at our life
and seeing what decisions
and what actions we made.
And in this case, we have
a great sentence here.
If I hadn't studied architecture,
I would have become an artist.
All right.
So let's look at the first
part before the comment.
If I hadn't studied architecture.
So now we have the conditional if.
So Mark, big question.
Did he study architecture?
He did.
So if I hadn't studied architecture,
I mean, I did study architecture.
But if I had not studied it.
Okay, so this is if I could change
the past, then what would I have done?
I would have become an artist.
Okay, so he wanted to be an
artist, but he didn't become an artist.
He studied architecture instead.
Right.
Very good.
You can see the two parts here.
We have won the condition
if I hadn't done this thing.
And then in the afterwards,
we have the result.
Then I would have become an artist.
So this is the hypothetical.
Very good.
And when we see the condition,
you see the gram, you see the
structure of the sentence is
had plus verb in past participle.
So if I hadn't studied architecture,
and this is called the past perfect.
Right.
And then the result, as you said, would
have become, this is the present perfect.
Have or has plus verb in past participle.
Let's look at another example.
I wouldn't have gotten married
if I hadn't moved to this town.
Okay, so we've got the same
idea here, but we've got it flipped.
We've got these two
parts in different places.
And so he's pretty much
saying, if I hadn't moved
to this town, then I
wouldn't have gotten married.
But what did happen?
He did move to this town,
and he did get married.
Exactly.
So then, yeah, like you say, he changed
the condition, and you can do this.
You can put the condition in
the beginning or at the end.
And again, the structure is the same.
I would have gotten married, right?
Have gotten this is present perfect.
Have or has, depending on the
subject, plus the verb in past participle.
And then the past perfect
or the condition had plus
verb in past participle
hadn't moved to this town.
All right.
That's a lot of grammar.
It's a lot of grammar, but it's very
easy once you just start using it.
I don't think too much
about, okay, what do I do here?
Just, you know, if you get
the rhythm and you start using
it in the same way, then it
kind of comes out naturally.
And if you make a little
mistake, there's not a big deal.
Because even we do it, you know?
Exactly.
Well, let's try a couple of examples
on the top of our heads first of all.
If I hadn't moved to China, I
wouldn't have learned Chinese.
Very good.
So you did move to China,
and you did learn China.
Exactly.
So your turn.
All right.
If my parents hadn't
spoken Spanish to me when I
was a kid, I wouldn't have
become fluent in Spanish.
Okay.
So your parents did speak Spanish, do you?
And you did be confined to Spanish.
So not bad.
Right.
As you can see, you can
use it not only to think about
things in the past that
you can't change anymore,
but just also, you know,
kind of remember or say,
you know, oh, if this
hadn't happened, the result.
Or if I hadn't opened my big mouth, my best
friend wouldn't have gotten so angry at me.
Exactly.
So I said something stupid,
and my friend did get angry.
And now I feel bad about it.
It happens.
All right.
Very good.
So I hope it's clear.
It does sound a little bit complicated,
but this is what our website is for, right?
So if you have questions or
doubts or you want to try and
plant your own ideas, you can
come to the website and do it.
Want to make some of your
own senses and practice some of
these new things then come to
our website, post some comments.
They're happy to correct and
add our own commentary on those.
Exactly.
So before we go, let's listen
to this dialogue one last time.
This is the good life.
We have a good, don't you think?
Yeah, of course.
Although, don't you ever
wonder what could have been?
What do you mean?
Well, sometimes I think
of how things could have
turned out if I had done
things a little differently.
For example, like for
example, if I hadn't studied
architecture, I would have
become an artist like I wanted to.
I see.
Yeah, now that I think of
it, I wouldn't have gotten
married if I hadn't moved
to this town and met Sally.
You see, everything happens for a reason.
We wouldn't even have met if I hadn't
been in that car accident ten years ago.
Well, I have no regrets.
I'll drink to that.
All right, we're back.
So Catherine, any other regrets, maybe in
your life apart from opening your mouth?
Any other regrets.
If my parents had spoken Spanish
to me as a kid, I would have learned.
But instead, I just learned
English and that's all.
Boy, your mom is a half Swedish, right?
Half Swedish, half Czech.
So, and she never spoke
any of these languages to you.
She, no, she didn't speak Swedish or Czech.
Her parents spoke English
as their common language,
but she grew up speaking
Italian and German.
But she didn't speak to
me in those languages.
And then as an adult, she forgot
some of them, some of them.
And so, because my dad was,
well, they're both Americans now.
But my dad's American.
They're just speaking English to me.
Well, but now you speak Italian, so do you
ever try and talk to your mom in Italian?
Sometimes.
My grandmother's Italian is much better,
so my grandmother's completely fluent.
So I speak to her in Italian.
And German as well.
She's fluent in German, too.
And I spotted German at school, so.
See, this is the interesting thing now.
So many people are
speaking so many languages.
And before, if you spoke another
foreign language, it was a big deal.
But now it's like a requirement.
You have to at least
dominate your own native
language and a
foreign language, right?
So if your native language
is English, you at least
have to speak Spanish or
Chinese or some other language.
Definitely true.
And I think there are
a lot of people, a lot of
our users that speak maybe
two or three languages.
And English is just one more.
So, you know, more power to them.
This is a really great skill to have.
And I think it's really
important to keep on
going with it, even
though it's frustrating.
And actually, once you've
been able, and actually
once you mastered two
or three different languages,
then the fourth and
fifth just becomes easier.
Actually, it's true.
It sounds funny when
you hear it because you're
like, "How could it be
easier to learn more?
" But your brain starts to
understand patterns better, right?
And so it just becomes
more natural for you.
It picks up patterns
from the two or three
other different languages
that you dominate.
So it's a weird, strange
how the brain works.
You mean connection?
Yeah.
So that's all for today.
Be sure to visit our
website, EnglishPod.com.
As we said, any questions
or comments or you
want us to correct your
grammar of this lesson.
You can visit us there and
we'll see you guys next time.
All right.
Bye, everyone.